<?xml version="1.0" standalone='no'?>
<!DOCTYPE spec SYSTEM "man.dtd">

<manpage name="masqmail.conf" section="5" desc="masqmail configuration file">

<description>
<p>This man page describes the syntax of the main configuration file
of masqmail. Its usual location is <file>/etc/masqmail.conf</file></p>

<p>The configuration consists of lines of the form</p>

<p><opt>val</opt> = <arg>expression</arg></p>

<p>Where <opt>val</opt> is a variable name and <arg>expression</arg> a string,
which can be quoted with '"'. If the expression is on multiple lines
or contains characters other than letters, digits or the characters
'.', '-', '_', '/', it <em>must</em> be quoted. You can use quotes inside quotes
by escaping them with a backslash.</p>

<p>Each val has a <i>type</i>, which can be boolean, numeric, string
or list. A boolean variable can be set with one of the values 'on',
'yes', and 'true' or 'off', 'no' and 'false'. List items are separated
with ';'. For some values patterns (like '*','?') can be used. The
spaces before and after the '=' are optional.</p>

<p>Most lists (exceptions: <opt>local_hosts</opt>,
<opt>local_nets</opt> and <opt>listen_addresses</opt>) accept
files. These will be recognized by a leading slash '/'. The contents
of these files will be included at the position of the file name,
there can be items or other files before and after the file entry. The
format of the files is different though, within these files each entry
is on another line. (And not separated by semicolons). This makes it
easy to include large lists which are common in different
configuration files, so they do not have to appear in every
configuration file.</p>

<p>Blank lines and lines starting with '#' are ignored.</p>

</description>

<options>
<option>
<p><opt>run_as_user = <arg>boolean</arg></opt></p>
<optdesc>
<p>If this is set, masqmail runs with the user id of the user who
invoked it and never changes it. This is for debugging purposes 
<em>only</em>. If the user is not root, masqmail will not be able to
listen on a port &lt; 1024 and will not be able to deliver local mail
to others than the user.</p>
</optdesc>
</option>

<option>
<p><opt>use_syslog = <arg>boolean</arg></opt></p>
<optdesc>
<p>If this is set, masqmail uses syslogd for logging. It uses facility
MAIL. You still have to set <opt>log_dir</opt> for debug files.</p>
</optdesc>
</option>

<option>
<p><opt>debug_level = <arg>n</arg></opt></p>
<optdesc>
<p>Set the debug level. Valid values are 0 to 6, increasing it further
makes no difference. Be careful if you set this as high as 5 or higher,
the logs may very soon fill your hard drive.</p>
</optdesc>
</option>

<option>
<p><opt>mail_dir = <arg>file</arg></opt></p>
<optdesc>
<p>The directory where local mail is stored,
usually <file>/var/spool/mail</file>.</p>
</optdesc>
</option>

<option>
<p><opt>spool_dir = <arg>file</arg></opt></p>
<optdesc>
<p>The directory where masqmail stores its spool files (and later also
other stuff). It <em>must</em> have a subdirectory <file>input</file>.
Masqmail needs read and write permissions for this
directory. I suggest to use <file>/var/spool/masqmail</file>.</p>
</optdesc>
</option>

<option>
<p><opt>host_name = <arg>string</arg></opt></p>
<optdesc>
<p>This is used in different places: Masqmail identifies itself in the
greeting banner on incoming connections and in the HELO/EHLO command
for outgoing connections with this name, it is used in the Received:
header and to qualify the sender of a locally originating message.</p>

<p>It is <em>not</em> used to find whether an address is local.
Use <opt>local_hosts</opt> for that.</p>
</optdesc>
</option>

<option>
<p><opt>remote_port = <arg>n</arg></opt></p>
<optdesc>
<p>The remote port number to be used. This defaults to port 25.</p>
</optdesc>
</option>

<option>
<p><opt>local_hosts = <arg>list</arg></opt></p>
<optdesc>
<p>A semicolon ';' separated list of hostnames which are considered
local. Normally you set it to "localhost;foo;foo.bar.com" if your host
has the fully qualified domain name 'foo.bar.com'.</p>
</optdesc>
</option>

<option>
<p><opt>local_nets = <arg>list</arg></opt></p>
<optdesc>
<p>A semicolon ';' separated list of hostnames which are on the
'local' net. Delivery to these hosts is attempted immediately. You can
use patterns with '*', eg. "*.bar.com".</p>
</optdesc>
</option>

<option>
<p><opt>listen_addresses = <arg>list</arg></opt></p>
<optdesc>
<p>A semicolon ';' separated list of interfaces on which connections
will be accepted. An interface ist defined by a hostname, optionally
followed by a colon ':' and a number for the port. If this is left out,
port 25 will be used.</p>
<p>You can set this to "localhost:25;foo:25" if your hostname is 'foo'.</p>
<p>Note that the names are resolved to IP addreses. If your host has
different names which resolve to the same IP, use only one of them,
otherwise you will get an error message and masqmail will
terminate.</p>
</optdesc>
</option>

<option>
<p><opt>do_queue = <arg>boolean</arg></opt></p>
<optdesc>
<p>If this is set, mail will not be delivered immediately when
accepted. Same as calling masqmail with the <opt>-odq</opt> option.</p>
</optdesc>
</option>

<option>
<p><opt>connect_route.<arg>name</arg> = <arg>list</arg></opt></p>
<optdesc>

<p>Replace <arg>name</arg> with a name to identify a connection. Set this
to a filename (or a list of filenames) for the special route configuration for that
connection. You will use that name to call masqmail with the
 <opt>-qo</opt> option every time a connection to your ISP is set
up.</p>

<p>Example: Your ISP has the name <i>FastNet</i>. Then you write the
following line in the main configuration:</p>

<p><opt>connect_route.FastNet</opt> = <arg>"/etc/masqmail/fastnet.route"</arg></p>

<p><file>/etc/masqmail/fastnet.route</file> is the route configuration
file, see <manref name="masqmail.route" section="5" href="masqmail.route.5.html"/>. As soon as a link to FastNet has been set up, you
call masqmail <opt>-qo</opt> <arg>FastNet</arg>. Masqmail will then
read the specified file and send the mails.</p>

</optdesc>
</option>

<option>
<p><opt>local_net_route = <arg>file</arg></opt></p>
<optdesc>
<p>This is similar to <opt>connect_route.<arg>name</arg></opt> but for the
local net. Recipient addresses that are in <b>local_nets</b> will be
routed using this route configuration. Main purpose is to define a
mail server with <b>mail_host</b> in your local network. In simple
environments this can be left unset. If unset, a default route
configuration will be used.</p>
</optdesc>
</option>

<option>
<p><opt>alias_file = <arg>file</arg></opt></p>
<optdesc>
<p>Set this to the location of your alias file. If unset, no aliasing
will be done.</p>
</optdesc>
</option>

<option>
<p><opt>alias_local_caseless = <arg>boolean</arg></opt></p>
<optdesc>
<p>If this is set, local parts in the alias file will be matched
disregarding upper/lower case.</p>
</optdesc>
</option>

<option>
<p><opt>pipe_fromline = <arg>boolean</arg></opt></p>
<optdesc>
<p>If this is set, a from line will be prepended to the output stream whenever
a pipe command is called after an alias expansion. Default is false.</p>
</optdesc>
</option>

<option>
<p><opt>pipe_fromhack = <arg>boolean</arg></opt></p>
<optdesc>
<p>If this is set, each line beginning with 'From ' is replaced with '>From ' whenever
a pipe command is called after an alias expansion. You probably want this if you have
set <opt>pipe_fromline</opt> above. Default is false.</p>
</optdesc>
</option>

<option>
<p><opt>mda = <arg>expand string</arg></opt></p>
<optdesc>
<p>If you want all local delivery to be transferred to an mda (Mail
Delivery Agent), set this to a command. The argument will be expanded
on delivery time, you can use variables beginning with a '$' sign,
optionally enclosed in curly braces. Variables you can use are:</p>
<p>uid - the unique message id. This is not necessarily identical with the Message ID as given in the Message ID: header.</p>
<p>received_host - the host the mail was received from</p>
<p>ident - the ident, this is either the ident delivered by the ident protocol or the user id of the sender if the message was received locally.</p>
<p>return_path_local - the local part of the return path (sender).</p>
<p>return_path_domain - the domain part of the return path (sender).</p>
<p>return_path - the complete return path (sender).</p>
<p>rcpt_local - the local part of the recipient.</p>
<p>rcpt_domain - the domain part of the recipient.</p>
<p>rcpt - the complete recipient address.</p>
<p>Example:</p><p>mda="/usr/bin/procmail -Y -d ${rcpt_local}"</p>
<p>For the mda, as for pipe commands, a few environment variables will
be set as well. See <manref name="masqmail" section="8"
href="masqmail.8.html"/>. To use environment variables for the mda,
the '$' sign has to be escaped with a backslash, otherwise they will
be tried to be expanded with the internal variables.</p>

</optdesc>
</option>

<option>
<p><opt>mda_fromline = <arg>boolean</arg></opt></p>
<optdesc>
<p>If this is set, a from line will be prepended to the output stream whenever
a message is delivered to an mda. Default is false.</p>
</optdesc>
</option>

<option>
<p><opt>mda_fromhack = <arg>boolean</arg></opt></p>
<optdesc>
<p>If this is set, each line beginning with 'From ' is replaced with '>From ' whenever
a message is delivered to an mda. You probably want this if you have
set <opt>mda_fromline</opt> above. Default is false.</p>
</optdesc>
</option>

<option>
<p><opt>online_detect = <arg>string</arg></opt></p>
<optdesc>
<p>Defines the method MasqMail uses to detect whether there is
currently an online connection. It can have the
values <opt>file</opt> or <opt>mserver</opt>.</p>

<p>When it is set to <opt>file</opt>, MasqMail first checks for the
existence of <opt>online_file</opt> (see below) and if it exists, it reads
it. The content of the file should be the name of the current
connection as defined with <opt>connect_route.<arg>name</arg></opt> (without
a trailing newline character).</p>

<p>When it is set to <opt>mserver</opt>, MasqMail connects to the
masqdialer server using the value of <opt>mserver_iface</opt> and asks it
whether a connection exists and for the name, which should be the name
of the current connection as defined with <opt>connect_route.<arg>name</arg></opt>.</p>

<p>No matter how MasqMail detects the online status, only messages
that are accepted at online time will be delivered using the
connection. The spool still has to be emptied with masqmail <opt>-qo</opt>
<arg>connection</arg>.</p>
</optdesc>
</option>

<option>
<p><opt>online_file = <arg>file</arg></opt></p>
<optdesc>
<p>This is the name of the file checked for when MasqMail determines
whether it is online. The file should only exist when there is
currently a connection. Create it in your ip-up script with eg.</p>

<p>echo -n &lt;name&gt; &gt; /tmp/connect_route</p>
<p>chmod 0644 /tmp/connect_route</p>

<p>Do not forget to delete it in your ip-down script.</p>
</optdesc>
</option>

<option>
<p><opt>mserver_iface = <arg>interface</arg></opt></p>
<optdesc>
<p>The interface the masqdialer server is listening to. Usually this
will be "localhost:224" if mserver is running on the same host as
masqmail. But using this option, you can also let masqmail run on
another host by setting <opt>mserver_iface</opt> to another hostname,
eg. "foo:224".</p>
</optdesc>
</option>

<option>
<p><opt>get.<arg>name</arg> = <arg>file</arg></opt></p>
<optdesc>
<p>Replace <arg>name</arg> with a name to identify a get
configuration. Set this to a filename for the get configuration. These
files will be used to retrieve mail when called with the -g option.</p>
</optdesc>
</option>

<option>
<p><opt>ident_trusted_nets = <arg>list</arg></opt></p>
<optdesc>
<p><arg>list</arg> is a list of networks of the form a.b.c.d/e
(eg. 192.168.1.0/24), from which the ident given by the ident protocol
will be trusted, so a user can delete his mail from the queue if the
ident is identical to his login name.</p>
</optdesc>
</option>

</options>

<section name = "Author">
<p>masqmail was written by Oliver Kurth
&lt;kurth@innominate.de&gt;</p><p>You will find the newest version of
masqmail at <url href="http://www.innomininate.org/~oku/masqmail/"/> or search for it
in freshmeat (<url href="http://www.freshmeat.net"/>). There is also a mailing list,
you will find information about it at masqmails main site.</p>
</section>

<section name = "Bugs">
<p>You should report them to the mailing list.</p>
</section>

<section name = "See also">
<p>
<manref name="masqmail" section="8" href="masqmail.8.html"/>, <manref name="masqmail.route" section="5" href="masqmail.route.5.html"/>, <manref name="masqmail.get" section="5" href="masqmail.get.5.html"/>
</p>
</section>


<section name = "Comments">
<p>This man page was written using <manref name="xml2man" section="1"
href="http://www.innominate.org/~oku/xml2man/"/> by the same
author.</p>
</section>

</manpage>

