<?xml version="1.0" standalone='no'?>
<!DOCTYPE spec SYSTEM "man.dtd">

<manpage name="masqmail.get" section="5" desc="masqmail get configuration file">

<description> <p>This man page describes the options available for the
masqmail get configuration.</p>

</description>

<options>

<option>
<p><opt>protocol</opt> = <arg>string</arg></p>
<optdesc>
<p>The protocol with which you retrieve your mail. Currently only
'pop3' and 'apop' are supported. There is no default.</p>
</optdesc>
</option>

<option>
<p><opt>server</opt> = <arg>string</arg></p>
<optdesc>
<p>The server you get your mail from.</p>
</optdesc>
</option>

<option>
<p><opt>resolve_list</opt> = <arg>list</arg></p>
<optdesc>
<p>Specify the method how the domain of the server is resolved. Possible values are
dns_mx, dns_a, byname. For 'dns_mx', the domain is assumed to be an MX
pointer to a list of host names, these will be tried each in order
(lowest preference value first, equal preference values in random
order). For 'dns_a', the domain is assumed to be an A pointer. For
'byname', the library function <manref name="gethostbyname" section="3"/> will be used.</p>
<p>The default is "dns_a;byname". It does not make much sense here to use 'dns_mx'.</p>
</optdesc>
</option>

<option>
<p><opt>user</opt> = <arg>string</arg></p>
<optdesc>
<p>Your login name.</p>
</optdesc>
</option>

<option>
<p><opt>pass</opt> = <arg>string</arg></p>
<optdesc>
<p>Your password.</p>
</optdesc>
</option>

<option>
<p><opt>address</opt> = <arg>string</arg></p>
<optdesc>
<p>The address where the retrieved mail should be sent to. It can be
any address, but you probably want to set this to a local address on
your LAN.</p>
</optdesc>
</option>

<option>
<p><opt>do_keep</opt> = <arg>boolean</arg></p>
<optdesc>
<p>If you want to keep your mail on the server after you retrieved it,
set this to true. It is recommended that you also set <b>do_uidl</b>,
otherwise you will get the mail again each time you connect to the
server. Masqmail does not check any headers before it retrieves mail,
which may mark it as already fetched.  Note that this behaviour is
different to that of fetchmail. The default is false.</p>
</optdesc>
</option>

<option>
<p><opt>do_uidl</opt> = <arg>boolean</arg></p>
<optdesc>
<p>If set, MasqMail keeps a list of unique IDs of mails already
fetched, so that they will not be retrieved again. Default is false.</p>
</optdesc>
</option>

<option>
<p><opt>max_size</opt> = <arg>numeric</arg></p>
<optdesc>
<p>If set to a value > 0, only messages smaller than this in bytes will be
retrieved. The default is 0.</p>
</optdesc>
</option>

<option>
<p><opt>wrapper</opt> = <arg>command</arg></p>
<optdesc>
<p>If set, instead of opening a connection to a remote server, <arg>command</arg> will
be called and all traffic will be piped to its
stdin and from its stdout. Purpose is to tunnel ip traffic, eg. for ssl.</p>
<p>Example for ssl tunneling:</p>
<p>wrapper="/usr/bin/openssl s_client -quiet -connect pop.gmx.net:995 2>/dev/null"</p>
</optdesc>
</option>

</options>

<section name = "Author">
<p>masqmail was written by Oliver Kurth
&lt;kurth@innominate.de&gt;</p><p>You will find the newest version of
masqmail at <url href="http://www.innomininate.org/~oku/masqmail/"/> or search for it
in freshmeat (<url href="http://www.freshmeat.net"/>). There is also a mailing list,
you will find information about it at masqmails main site.</p>
</section>

<section name = "Bugs">
<p>You should report them to the mailing list.</p>
</section>

<section name = "See also">
<p>
<manref name="masqmail" section="8" href="masqmail.8.html"/>, <manref name="masqmail.route" section="5" href="masqmail.route.5.html"/>, <manref name="masqmail.conf" section="5" href="masqmail.conf.5.html"/>
</p>
</section>

<section name = "Comments">
<p>This man page was written using <manref name="xml2man" section="1"
href="http://www.innominate.org/~oku/xml2man/"/> by the same
author.</p>
</section>

</manpage>

