<?xml version="1.0" standalone='no'?>
<!DOCTYPE spec SYSTEM "man.dtd">

<manpage name="masqmail.aliases" section="5" desc="masqmail alias file format">

<description>
<p>This man page describes the format of the masqmail alias file. Its usual location is <file>/etc/aliases</file>.</p>
</description>

<section name="File Format">
<p>The alias file consists of lines of the form:</p>
<pre>
local_part: item1, item2, ...
</pre>

<p>Items can be surrounded by quotes '"'. If within the quotes other
quotes are needed for an address they can be escaped with a leading
backslash '\'.</p>

<p>A leading '\' indicates that this address shall not be further
expanded.</p>

<p>A leading pipe symbol '|' indicates that the item shall be treated
as a pipe command. The content of the message will then be sent to the
standard input of a command. The command will run under the user id
and group id masqmail is running as. If quotes are needed, the pipe
symbol must appear <i>within</i> the quotes.</p>

<p>Loops will be detected, the offending address will be ignored.</p>

<p>Aliases will be expanded at <i>delivery</i> time. This means that
if there is a message still in the queue and you change any alias
which matches one of the recipient addresses, the change will have
effect next time a delivery is attemped.</p>

<p>There is no need to restart masqmail or run any command when the
alias file has been changed.</p>
</section>

<section name = "Author">
<p>masqmail was written by Oliver Kurth
&lt;oku@masqmail.cx&gt;</p><p>You will find the newest version of
masqmail at <url href="http://masqmail.cx/masqmail/"/> or search for it
in freshmeat (<url href="http://www.freshmeat.net"/>). There is also a mailing list,
you will find information about it at masqmails main site.</p>
</section>

<section name = "Bugs">
<p>You should report them to the mailing list.</p>
</section>

<section name = "See also">
<p>
<manref name="masqmail.conf" section="5" href="masqmail.conf.5.html"/>, <manref name="masqmail" section="8" href="masqmail.8.html"/>, 
</p>
</section>

<section name = "Comments">
<p>This man page was written using <manref name="xml2man" section="1"
 href="http://masqmail.cx/xml2man/"/> by the same author.</p>
</section>

</manpage>
